<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" "document-v12.dtd">
<document> 
  <header> 
    <title>External Components</title> 
    <authors>
      <person name="Shane Curcuru" email="curcuru@apache.org"/> 
    </authors> 
  </header> 
  <body> 
    <section id="overview">
      <title>Overview</title>
      <p>xml-commons provides an Apache-hosted set of DOM, SAX, and JAXP interfaces for use in 
      other xml-based projects.  Our hope is that we can standardize on both a common version and 
      packaging scheme for these critical XML standards interfaces to make the lives of both 
      our developers and users easier.         
      </p>
      <p>The External Components portion of xml-commons contains interfaces that 
      are defined by external standards organizations.  For DOM, that's the W3c; for SAX it's 
      David Megginson and sax.sourceforge.net; for JAXP it's Sun.  While we could send users to 
      each of the primary sources for these deliverables, keeping our own versions of these in 
      the xml-commons repository gives us a number of advantages:
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>Simplicity of downloads: users get the whole product from one place.
        </li>
        <li>Better version control: we can only take fixes we want, and add Apache-specific changes.
        </li>
        <li>Better overview documentation of how these interfaces fit into the XML processing world.
        </li>
        <li>More chance for cross-project community building within Apache projects.
        </li>
      </ul>

    <fixme author="curcuru">In progress.  See the commons-dev-at-xml.apache.org mailing list 
    for our current progress at updating the structure of the xml-commons project.  Volunteers 
    to help with the documentation set appreciated as well!
    </fixme>
    <p>Currently, we provide just the native sets of javadoc from each of these external 
    sets of code, plus whatever native documentation provided.  
    We also include LICENSE and README files for each set of code from 
    an external source.
    </p>
      
      </section>

  </body>
</document>
